<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[David Virtser]]></title>
  <link href="http://virtser.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://virtser.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-05T20:30:27+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://virtser.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Virtser]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[poison77@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fujifilm X100S Tips &amp; Tricks]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/11/24/fujifilm-x100s-tips-and-tricks/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-24T23:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/11/24/fujifilm-x100s-tips-and-tricks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To alter slightly, this one is not a technical R&amp;D world related post, but my photograpjy hobby related one. Hope you don&#8217;t mind? Will followup with pictures. :)</p>

<p><img src="http://www.imaging-resource.com/ee_uploads/news/1391/x100s-front.jpg" alt="Fujifilm X100S" /></p>

<p>My <a href="http://www.dpreview.com/reviews/fujifilm-x100s">Fuji X100S</a> is on its way to me. I&#8217;m so excited about it that I started to learn more about it before I actually got it. </p>

<p>It took me a while to read all the articles in the Internet about the camera until I decided to order one and took some notes with all the useful pieces of information that I found in the Internet with references for myself.</p>

<p>But I think that it would be a good idea to share this list with you in random order as I noted (some notes may repeat). I hope you can find something new and useful there for you too. </p>

<!-- more -->


<p><strong>1. </strong>In good lighting and with the focusing point made the largest, this camera is a focusing speed demon and perhaps right up there with Olympus’s FAST AF system. Make it smaller, and you have something on par with Canon’s EOS M camera.</p>

<p>And once again, we really need to recommend that you don’t focus and recompose with this camera. Sure it might be easier, but you’re just throwing off the focusing plane.<br/>
<a href="http://www.thephoblographer.com/2013/03/25/using-the-fujifilm-x100s-for-street-photography/">www.thephoblographer.com/2013/03/25/using-the-fujifilm-x1&#8230;</a></p>

<p><strong>2. </strong>The sweet spot with the X100s is to shoot on (L)100 ISO, at 1/1000th of a sec at f/2 with the built-in 3-stop ND filter engaged. That will underexpose full daylight. You can then overpower the sun with a small flash and shoot wide open in the process for gorgeous backgrounds at f/2<br/>
<a href="http://strobist.blogspot.co.il/2013/05/leaf-shutter-nd-flash-fuji-x100s.html">strobist.blogspot.co.il/2013/05/leaf-shutter-nd-flash-fuj&#8230;</a></p>

<p><strong>3.</strong> lose the slip-on lens cap and get a hood and a 49mm skylight filter. And not a crap filter, either, as the aspherical 23mm/2 (35mm/2 equiv.) lens deserves good glass in front. Put the lens cap in a drawer and go filter/hood full-time.<br/>
<a href="http://strobist.blogspot.fr/2013/03/in-depth-new-fujifilm-x100s.html">strobist.blogspot.fr/2013/03/in-depth-new-fujifilm-x100s&#8230;.</a></p>

<p><strong>4. </strong>I normally configure my custom settings for +1 Color Boost and +1 Sharpness.</p>

<p>Function Button – You can assign a variety of functions to the function button (FN) for quick access. Things like ISO, ND Filter, Film Simulation etc. During the day, I set mine to turn off/on the ND filter. At night, or if I’m in a situation where I need ISO control, I’ll set it to ISO.<br/>
<a href="http://www.hossedia.com/reviews/fuji-x100s-review/">www.hossedia.com/reviews/fuji-x100s-review/</a></p>

<p><strong>5. </strong>Great review and reason why x100s that convinced me<br/>
<a href="http://www.mitchellkphotos.com/blog/2013/10/15/istanbul-and-my-review-of-fuji-x100s/">www.mitchellkphotos.com/blog/2013/10/15/istanbul-and-my-r&#8230;</a></p>

<p><strong>6. </strong>Fujix x100s collection of all materials found in the net <br/>
<a href="https://sites.google.com/site/wosimsphotography/fuji-x100s-testberichte-reviews">sites.google.com/site/wosimsphotography/fuji-x100s-testbe&#8230;</a></p>

<p><strong>7. </strong>If you use mostly the opti­cal finder, turn the “OVF power save mode” on. The display’s info will be dimmed a bit, and the live his­togram is no longer avail­able, but it will greatly extend the bat­tery life. I strongly rec­om­mend read­ing pages 18, 36, 41, 47, and 91 from the Camera’s Instruc­tion Man­ual.<br/>
<a href="http://www.eduardoangel.com/2013/11/12/fuji-x100s-hands-on-review/">www.eduardoangel.com/2013/11/12/fuji-x100s-hands-on-review/</a></p>

<p><strong>8. </strong>B&amp;W shooting tips:<br/>
My favorite B&amp;W setting on the X100S for most situations are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Film simulation: B-R (B&amp;W Red Filter)</li>
<li>Sharpness: +1</li>
<li>Highlight Tone: 0</li>
<li>Shadow Tone: +1</li>
<li>Noise Reduction: -2</li>
</ul>


<p>And in case you don&#8217;t have a lot of experience with B&amp;W photography the Fuji X cameras with EVF or LCD will take you by the hand and guide you to your first successful exposures. When you switch your JPG to B&amp;W you will see a B&amp;W image in the EVF / LCD preview. Now use the exposure compensation dial (in Aperture priority mode) to increase or decrease the exposure and get a more predominant black or white look.</p>

<p>Still not sure if you want to deprive your exposures of the color for good? No problem! Set the Fuji X100S to shoot JPG + RAW and the RAW file will contain all of the color information just in case you change your mind later. The EVF will still show the B&amp;W preview.</p>

<p>So, are you ready to give it a try? Then why not just save the B&amp;W settings as one of your custom settings in your X100S for those occasions when you feel like shooting Monochrome :)<br/>
<a href="http://fujixfiles.blogspot.co.il/2013/10/the-Fuji-X100S-made-me-a-better-BW-photographer.html">fujixfiles.blogspot.co.il/2013/10/the-Fuji-X100S-made-me-&#8230;</a></p>

<p><strong>9. </strong>If maximum operating speed is important to you, then switch off all energy saving- and switch on all performance improving features. What also helps is when you use the fastest UHS-I SDHC cards. But with all energy saving turned off, I highly recommend that you buy at least one, or better yet, two spare batteries for your X100S.</p>

<p>The lens picks up some flare and this is identical to the lens on the original X100. Hence, I would buy the lens hood with adapter for two reasons:<br/>
A. To control flare.<br/>
B. To have a filter thread for the use of filter or simply to plug in a standard lens cap (49mm filter and lens cap for the adapter without the lens hood and a 52mm lens cap for use with the lens hood attached - you can see this on the second photo from the top). And do get the lens caps with the pinch release in the middle of the cap!</p>

<p>The X100S has turned into my every day take along camera. It is my street, portrait and city/landscape tool. And, I use it 95% of the time as a B&amp;W camera! I set the camera to record JPG + RAW and set the JPG to be captured in BW + Red Filter. This way the EVF and the review image in the EVF &amp; OVF will show a B&amp;W image which is closest to the way I would process it. The RAW file still contains the color information and will be rendered as a color image in my LightRoom collection, next to the B&amp;W JPG image.</p>

<p>I find that seeing a scene in B&amp;W is less distracting and lets me focus more intensely on the subject and situation of the scene.</p>

<p>These are my preferred every day settings when I&#8217;m out with the X100S:</p>

<ul>
<li>Fn = ND Filter (heavily used in bright conditions to overcome the f2 &amp; 1/1000s limit)</li>
<li>RAW + JPG</li>
<li>ISO: Auto 6400 at 1/100s (I&#8217;d rather take a bit more noise than motion blur)</li>
<li>Film simulation: B-R (B&amp;W Red Filter)</li>
<li>Sharpness: +1</li>
<li>Highlight Tone: 0</li>
<li>Shadow Tone: +1</li>
<li>Noise Reduction: -2</li>
<li>MF Assist: Max</li>
<li>High Performance Mode: On</li>
<li>Power Saving: Off</li>
<li>Review Time: 0.5 S</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://fujixfiles.blogspot.co.il/2013/07/Fuji-X100S-Review-is-it-worth-to-upgrade.html">fujixfiles.blogspot.co.il/2013/07/Fuji-X100S-Review-is-it&#8230;</a></p>

<p><strong>10. </strong>Focusing tips relevant for x100s as well <br/>
<a href="http://www.fujixfiles.blogspot.co.il/2012/08/fuji-x-pro-1-af-autofocus-speed-and.html">www.fujixfiles.blogspot.co.il/2012/08/fuji-x-pro-1-af-aut&#8230;</a></p>

<p><strong>11.</strong> Optical viewfinder prallax explained in details <br/>
<a href="http://theonlinephotographer.typepad.com/the_online_photographer/2011/07/ps-to-the-fuji-x100-review-parallax.html">theonlinephotographer.typepad.com/the_online_photographer&#8230;</a></p>

<p><strong>12. </strong> When you are shooting objects that quickly move towards the camera, better use the famous “Autofocus Trick”, also known as “shutter mash technique”: Set the camera to AF-S or AF-C (use AF-S if you want to assign a particular AF field, use AF-C if you are okay with the center spot or area) and press the shutter all the way through in one quick, swift motion (no half-pressing!) while keeping the AF field trained over the area of your subject that you want to be in focus. Since the X100S operates with Autofocus Priority, it won’t take the shot until it has actually locked focus (or until it gave up, in which case the shot will probably be wasted).</p>

<p>Shortcuts:</p>

<ul>
<li>Press and hold the Q button for a few seconds to clearly increase the brightness of the LCD. This can be quite helpful when operating the camera in bright light, like on a sunny day.</li>
<li>Press and hold the MENU/OK button down to lock or unlock the arrow keys and the Q button.</li>
<li>A long press of the Fn button will bring up the Fn button’s configuration menu, where you can assign one of several functions. I typically assign ISO to this button, because I like to be able to quickly change my Auto-ISO configuration (minimum shutter speed). Another popular option for this button is enabling the camera’s built-in ND filter.</li>
<li>Press and hold DISP/BACK button to activate (or deactivate) the camera’s Silent Mode. When this mode is turned on, the X100S functions quietly and inconspicuously. It won’t make any artificial noises and it abstains from using both the flash and the AF-assist lamp.</li>
<li>Pressing the DISP/BACK button while selecting an AF field in AF-S Area mode will immediately select the central AF field.</li>
<li>Press DISP/BACK in shooting or playback mode to change the view of the currently active display. This means that in order to change the view of either the OVF, the EVF or the LCD, either the OVF, EVF or LCD must be active when you press the button. You can select the display you want to change with the VIEW MODE button. Alternatively, use the eye-sensor to activate a display by looking through it, then change its view with the DISP/BACK button. The X100S can’t read your mind, you need to tell it which display’s view you want to change. </li>
<li>Finally, to check (or upgrade) the firmware version of the camera, press and hold the DISP/BACK button while switching on the camera.</li>
<li>In manual focus mode, press the AE-L/AF-L button to initiate an autofocus run.</li>
<li>Also in manual focus mode, press and hold the command dial to cycle through the camera’s different MF aids: standard, digital split image and focus peaking.</li>
<li>Press (but do not hold) the command dial to enlarge the current image to inspect its sharpness. This works in both MF and AF modes.</li>
<li>Rather than selecting a function in the shooting menu by pressing the OK button, you can press the shutter button halfway down. Pressing the shutter button halfway down while in playback mode switches the camera directly into shooting mode. You can wake the camera by pressing the shutter button halfway down as well.</li>
<li>Double-tap the macro button to switch between normal and macro modes.</li>
</ul>


<p><a href="http://www.fujirumors.com/using-the-x100s/">www.fujirumors.com/using-the-x100s/</a></p>

<p><strong>13.</strong> List of Fuji x!00s useful accessories</p>

<p><a href="http://www.bestmirrorlesscamerareviews.com/2013/11/05/best-fuji-x100s-accessories/">www.bestmirrorlesscamerareviews.com/2013/11/05/best-fuji-&#8230;</a></p>

<p><strong>14.</strong> JJC hood and B+W Pro filter: Protection. spend a few dollars, put these on and keep them there. I don&#8217;t use a cap on this camera (they come off and I lose them). But don&#8217;t use a cheap filter. B + W are the best. German made, pure optics. Whats the point of having a camera with the best sensor and glass, if you stick cheap distorted junk in front of it. $50 won&#8217;t break the bank! The hood stops glare and adds more protection. You can spend $$ for the fuji one, or $ for a nasty el cheapo. Spend $ and get the JJC. as good as the real thing, but not flimsy.</p>

<p><a href="http://ed-jones.squarespace.com/blog/2013/11/16/the-cliche-whats-in-my-bag-post">ed-jones.squarespace.com/blog/2013/11/16/the-cliche-whats&#8230;</a></p>

<p><strong>More Updates:</strong></p>

<p><strong>15.</strong> Auto-ISO settings discussion - I&#8217;m finding ISO 6400 is just fine, in fact amazing on this camera so I &#8216;ve set my minimum speed at 1/125.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.fujixspot.com/showthread.php?t=853">http://www.fujixspot.com/showthread.php?t=853</a></p>

<p><strong>16.</strong> In video shooting if you are stuggling with automatic focus, set aperture and shutter to Automatic mode and choose AF-C mode to get constant continues focus.</p>

<p><strong>17.</strong> Unless you are doing macro work with f2 then it works perfectly fine in most cases. The focal length of this lens gives you a larger depth of field anyway. Anything farther away than about 5 feet and at any aperture above 2.8 should be just fine for focus and recompose.</p>

<p>Hope you liked it.<br/>
If you have more tips &amp; tricks to add to the list, please leave in comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Re-Culturing a 200 employees Start-Up Video]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/10/25/re-culturing-a-200-employees-start-up-video/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-25T15:51:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/10/25/re-culturing-a-200-employees-start-up-video</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Our talk with Dvir Greenberg for DevOpsDays TLV 2013 conference:</p>

<iframe src="http://virtser.net//player.vimeo.com/video/77674916?title=0" width="600" height="337" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p> <p><a href="http://vimeo.com/77674916">Re-Culturing a 200 employee start-up - David Virtser and Dvir Greenberg</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/devopsdays">devopsdays</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Re-culturing a 200 employees startup]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/10/02/re-culturing-a-200-employees-start-up/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-02T19:52:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/10/02/re-culturing-a-200-employees-start-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://devopsdays.org/events/2013-telaviv/">DevOpsDays TLV</a> conference is over and it was awesome! Learned a lot, listen to some very cool presentations, met new people and even give a talk!</p>

<p>I&#8217;m not the guy for great speeches, but still it was an amazing experience for me. People asked questions and was interested in the process we are running. We tried to be as open and transparent as possible, showing the good and bad things in the process. I hope it worked and we will be able to help others to kick-off the process in their organizations.  Will be happy to get your feedback.</p>

<p>Find below the slides from our presentation about DevOps implementation in <a href="http://www.etoro.com">eToro</a>:</p>

<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/26739176?rel=0" width="597" height="486" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p></p>

<p>Composed and presented by Dvir Greenberg and David Virtser.</p>

<p>If you have some questions or want to talk about DevOps implementation process in medium size organization, don&#8217;t hesitate to contact me.</p>

<p>Our speech recording will follow.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[eToro DevOps Progress]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/09/19/etoro-devops-progress/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-19T14:01:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/09/19/etoro-devops-progress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A little spoiler for our <a href="http://devopsdays.org/events/2013-telaviv/">DevOpsDays TLV</a> presentation which is going to take place 30 Sep - 01 Oct. :)</p>

<p>I want to share with you one slide of eToro DevOps progress in the last 4 months:</p>

<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/devopsprogress.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>I know it&#8217;s not much, but considering our current size and cultural gaps we had, I&#8217;m very satisfied!</p>

<p>Only this month we finally completed the recruitment of DevOps team.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Continuous Delivery Vision]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/08/14/continuous-delivery-vision/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-14T19:27:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/08/14/continuous-delivery-vision</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Find below a presentation of eToro Continuous Delivery vision as recently composed and presented by our CD leader <a href="https://twitter.com/alonbecker">Alon Becker</a>.</p>

<iframe src="http://prezi.com/embed/kinvydtyaj4p/?bgcolor=ffffff&amp;lock_to_path=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;autohide_ctrls=0&amp;features=undefined&amp;disabled_features=undefined" width="600" height="400" frameBorder="0"></iframe>


<p>We still have a very long way full of challenges in front of us to get to CD, but the train left a station…</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mercurial over Kiln tips and tricks]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/07/23/mercurial-over-kiln-tips-and-tricks/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-23T22:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/07/23/mercurial-over-kiln-tips-and-tricks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I want to share with you the slides that I created and presented to eToro R&amp;D to get introduced with more advanced features and options of Mercurial and Kiln.</p>

<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/22784525" width="597" height="486" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p>Hope you find it helpful.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Velocity and DevOpsDays]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/07/02/velocity-and-devopsdays/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-02T21:25:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/07/02/velocity-and-devopsdays</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, it took me a while to get back to life after a huge jet lag hit me badly. Surprisingly, it wasn&#8217;t that hard when I went from here to San Francisco, but it was much harder to come back to Israel. 10 hour difference in time zones do the thing.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m back from 10 days business and pleasure trip to Bay Area - San Francisco, Santa Clara, Mountain View, Paulo Alto, Cupertino, Saratoga (AKA Silicon Valley), San Jose and Santa Cruz. Here is a classic postcard picture I took in San Francisco:</p>

<p><img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7294/9138679173_f71502b827_b.jpg" alt="Golden Gate Bridge © David Virtser" /></p>

<p>We spent 2 days in San Francisco just traveling for pleasure,  followed by 4 intensive days of <a href="http://velocityconf.com/velocity2013/">Velocity</a> and <a href="http://devopsdays.org/events/2012-mountainview/">DevOpsDays</a> conferences in Santa Clara. The former is expensive, very big, public, focused on Web Performance and Operations. The latter is small, private, focused of DevOps culture.</p>

<p>The conferences were different, but both very good. The reason I go there was to learn more about DevOps culture from experience of real companies and people who do it in modern web industry. Companies like Facebook, Twitter, Google, Netflix and others.</p>

<p>Few insights that I marked to myself and were repeated over and over again on number of different sessions which are important for a company to be Agile/Lean:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Make a focus</strong> - Great companies do one product, but do it outstanding. They focus on their product whole holistic experience - how it looks, how it feels, how responsive is it, how reliable is it, how easy is it, how intuitive is it, how much time does it take to get an answer from customer support and etc… They invest most of the time in robust and scalable infrastructure, in performance of the applications, in fixing bugs, optimizing and analyzing.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Recruit professionals</strong> - experienced, full-stack developers are expensive, but in long run they worth it. You can have a lot of developers with potential, but still they need a senior to show them the right path and explain how things work in real world.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Logging &amp; Monitoring</strong> - more than half of the booths and sessions in conferences where about monitoring and measuring of applications in production. It&#8217;s extremely important to invest in this area. The tools that where mentioned the most: <a href="http://graphite.wikidot.com/">Graphite</a>, <a href="http://newrelic.com/">New Relic</a>, <a href="http://logstash.net/">logstash</a>/<a href="http://www.splunk.com/">Splunk</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Open source everything</strong> - open sourcing your code is coming with great responsibility to support the community (pull request, issues), but it also teaches you how to write good application -  tests, documentation, generic code, etc.. If you do it right, you will get help back from community. Open sourcing is social  programming.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Bootcamps</strong> - workshops, lectures. It&#8217;s a common practice. Do it more to train your people and get them involved.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Microsoft</strong> - Windows, .NET world is a dead end. It&#8217;s hardly  scalable (MS SQL Server), slower (IIS), harder to operate, complicated automation, requires stronger hardware and more.</p></li>
</ol>


<p><img src="http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5443/9193469533_f4f7381ea7_b.jpg" alt="No comments © David Virtser" /></p>

<p>We are definitely going to work on all of these in eToro.</p>

<p>Few videos from the conferences which I liked and inspired me the most:</p>

<p><a href="http://vimeo.com/album/2435220/video/69079272">Leading the Horses to Drink &#8230; Support and Initiate a devops transformation</a></p>

<p><a href="http://vimeo.com/album/2435220/video/69078828">Devops+Agile = Business Transformation</a></p>

<p><a href="http://vimeo.com/album/2435220/video/69079946">Continuous Quality</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RGFGdFS_3Cc&amp;list=SP055Epbe6d5bdB4KPqssegVpYUDJXSzOp&amp;index=16">f You Don&#8217;t Understand People, You Don&#8217;t Understand Ops</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LCZT_Q3z520&amp;list=SP055Epbe6d5bdB4KPqssegVpYUDJXSzOp&amp;index=12">Gamedays on the Obama Campaign</a></p>

<p>That&#8217;s it for today. See you at <a href="http://devopsdays.org/events/2013-telaviv/">DevOpsDays Tel-Aviv</a>. eToro is going to sponsor this event and hopefully we will be able to present our journey there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[eToro Openbook SEO Implementation]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/06/06/etoro-openbook-seo/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-06T20:05:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/06/06/etoro-openbook-seo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes in eToro we are doing really innovative and beautiful things.</p>

<p>In our <a href="https://openbook.etoro.com">Openbook</a> web application most of the calls are executed on client side using Ajax. Which means that our pages content is  changing dynamically. Google bots can index static content pages only.</p>

<p>It was a challenge to find a good and easy to implement solution which required minimum of changes on <a href="https://openbook.etoro.com">Openbook</a> itslef.</p>

<p>Find below the presentation explaining our solution:</p>

<iframe src="http://prezi.com/embed/8jncrjqi204a/?bgcolor=ffffff&amp;lock_to_path=0&amp;autoplay=0&amp;autohide_ctrls=0&amp;features=undefined&amp;disabled_features=undefined" width="600" height="400" frameBorder="0"></iframe>


<p>All the credits for the presentation goes to Omry Hay, for design to <a href="http://gal-segal.net">Gal Segal</a> &amp; Shlomi Shemesh and for implementation to Shomi Shemesh, the one and only!</p>

<p>P.S.
If you are interested we can open source this Node.js SEO solution. Let me know in comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[eToro is looking for DevOps engineers]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/05/29/etoro-is-looking-for-devops-engineers/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-29T21:34:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/05/29/etoro-is-looking-for-devops-engineers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are open minded, have a vision and potential, got wide process understanding, passionate about building CI/CD process, don&#8217;t afraid of writing code (hacking), like to explore new domains, don&#8217;t want to manage people, like challenges, understand DevOps culture, live in Israel and have experience in Dev, DBA, IT, Ops or CM - <a href="http://www.etoro.com">eToro</a> is looking for you!</p>

<p>Please comment with questions or <a href="http://virtser.net/about">contact me</a> in private.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Future of eToro R&amp;D]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/05/26/future-of-etoro-r-and-d/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-26T23:03:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/05/26/future-of-etoro-r-and-d</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/EToro_logo_facebook_profile.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Few months ago we started to get the vibes of change.</p>

<p>I think all started when <a href="http://www.etoro.com">eToro</a> hosted it&#8217;s first private <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hackathon">Hackathon</a>. All the company activities where paused for 48 hours in favor of the hack. Everyone could join the effort from HR to R&amp;D teams. It was an amazing experience, when ideas of people who never had a chance to make a change and create something for our customers where chosen and brought to live.</p>

<p>We started thinking and talking about <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flat_organization">flat organization</a> structure, how do we implement and encourage developers mobility in teams. A new term &#8220;Develorship&#8221; was introduces, which is talking about that any independent developer can take and lead a projects A to Z. We are working to shift the power of choice from Product to Development of what is important to ship now.</p>

<p>Followed by our visit to <a href="http://www.wix.com/">Wix</a>, a successful Israeli company which does <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_delivery">Continues Delivery</a> and host millions of customized websites. At <a href="http://www.wix.com/">Wix</a> we met <a href="http://www.aviransplace.com">Aviran Mordo</a>, a Back-end Group Manager, who gave us a <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/aviranwix/scaling-up-to-30-m-users">presentation</a> about the switch to Continues Delivery that they did and answered a lot of our questions.</p>

<p>After the visit we started to read and think about Continues Delivery and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DevOps">DevOps</a>. How do we optimize our process? How do we make non blocking development? How do we automate everything that can be automated? And more questions that should be answered… We realized that we can&#8217;t continue the same way we did until now and we need to think how to get to Continues Delivery.</p>

<p>To answer these questions, a DevOps forum was established. A forum of 5 key people from each department in R&amp;D. I was one of them. It&#8217;s mission was to map our problems in current development process and suggest a plan how to implement Continues Delivery in the company.</p>

<p>After few offsite meeting of the forum we mapped all the problems and suggested an aggressive plan how to get to Continues Delivery in about 1 year. The plan included two parts:</p>

<p>1) Establishment of dedicated DevOps team to work on R&amp;D culture, make a focus on Continues Integration and Delivery process, establish logging &amp; monitoring expertise, minimize our gaps in Database automation and reorganization of our IT department main processes.</p>

<p>2) Working with existing R&amp;D teams to learn and implement Test Driven Development, write more unit tests, write integration test, implement more test automation to make our regressions test faster and more efficient, working on better logging &amp; monitoring of our existing systems, etc…</p>

<p>The plan was delivered to the management and we got their blessing  and full backup to go for it. Without management support you can&#8217;t do it. To start working on #2 immediately freestyle Tuesdays where established in the company. A free day of regular iteration work where people can choose what they work on. It can be check your production logs, write more tests, do some automation, listen to lectures, anything that can make your work process better.</p>

<p>I was chosen and volunteered to lead the DevOps effort in the company as I have the experience and understanding of the processes in the company just because I work in <a href="http://www.etoro.com">eToro</a> since the beginning. I left my previous role of managing few R&amp;D teams and established a new DevOps team which I&#8217;m working at the moment on it&#8217;s recruitment.</p>

<p>We realize that there is a lot of work to be done, we have a lot of cultural and technological gaps, but now we have an isolated environment to make the focus to work on <a href="http://www.etoro.com">eToro</a> R&amp;D strategy and bring the change.</p>

<p>P.S.</p>

<p>Stay tuned to get updated on our progress as time goes by.</p>

<p>Hope you enjoy the story. :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Current status of eToro R&amp;D]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/05/08/current-status-of-etoro-r-and-d/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-08T22:35:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/05/08/current-status-of-etoro-r-and-d</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/eToro.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>When I refer to current R&amp;D status, I refer to the situation which was relevant for about 3 months ago. Not that today it is very  different, but what started in <a href="http://www.etoro.com">eToro</a> 3 months ago I&#8217;m going to call the future of <a href="http://www.etoro.com">eToro</a> R&amp;D. And I&#8217;m going to cover it in next  post.</p>

<p>Anyway, lets talk about the current R&amp;D status. We are big and we are getting bigger all the time. We are about 70 employees in R&amp;D (including developers, QA, DBAs and IT).</p>

<p>We have migrated from SVN to Mercurial revision control system. SVN was really bad with dealing with branch merges. Openbook was a big team of 8 people and it was impossible to continue with SVN. We wanted to work using <a href="http://nvie.com/posts/a-successful-git-branching-model/">feature branch model</a>. Our only two candidates were Git and Mercurial, both are very similar and fit our needs. We chose Mercurial because we are using <a href="http://www.fogcreek.com/fogbugz/">FogBugz</a> as our bug tracking system and FogCreek released <a href="http://www.fogcreek.com/kiln/">Kiln</a>, a Mercurial server which has a tight integration with FogBugz.</p>

<p>Shared static environments problems is a daily talk and everybody knows that dealing with configuration changes or fixing a broken environment can take hours, sometimes days. There is no integration environment where we can test cross R&amp;D developments. We have to work in the office, because we are dependant in our network, we have no mocks.</p>

<p>We have a lot of dependencies, we wait for QA to finish, we wait for DBA to write the script, we wait for IT to deploy application, we wait for IT to see our logs in production in case of troubleshooting. We are doing blocking development.</p>

<p>We have sort of monitoring in production using <a href="https://logentries.com/">LogEntries</a> and <a href="http://newrelic.com/">New Relic</a> which gives us more information, but we still can&#8217;t find the source of the problem when we have crisis.</p>

<p>In the past year we slowly started to learn and implement Test Driven Development process in few teams, writing unit tests. Still not enough, product can hardly understand/feel the impact of these tests. Same goes with peer code reviews. We have no test automation at all, our manual regression test takes 3 days of 2 QA people.</p>

<p>About a year ago we recruited configuration manager who started with build automation in teams. Nowadays most of the projects are built automatically. Deployments are still done manually to all environments.</p>

<p>We have no performance test lab, but we already starting to feel the impact of customers growth in production. All the problems are found in productions.</p>

<p>We have very few DBs, some are really big with a lot of shared objects, no APIs on shared objects. We have no scripts to create clean DB with just the schema. Our DBs should be separated to small DBs. DB revision control is awkward.</p>

<p>In the last year we made a transition in most of the teams from Waterfall to Agile software development methodology. It gave us a new breath, short releases (once in 2-3 weeks), more visibility of the process, tools to measure the process and get improved. From other hand it also emphasized our downsides, our dependencies, risks we take. It is still hard to manage it, we have delays in iterations, we commit to stories which we don&#8217;t deliver and we deliver stories which we didn&#8217;t commit to.</p>

<p>We feel that we are not scalable internally. We afraid to recruit another team member, because it won&#8217;t increase our performance, it will decrease it and I was able to prove that.</p>

<p>It is a heavy and slow machine which can hardly move&#8230;</p>

<p>P.S.
Next post will be much more positive. ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[History of development process in eToro]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/05/01/history-of-development-process-in-etoro/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-01T08:02:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/05/01/history-of-development-process-in-etoro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/logo.jpg" alt="First eToro logo - 2007" /></p>

<p>It&#8217;s all started for me about 6 years ago, summer 2007. I left another startup in gambling industry in favor of <a href="http://www.etoro.com">eToro</a>, which looked very promising to me. I had an experience of few years as webmaster and web developer and I was at my last year of computer science studies in a collage. My main mission was to establish company websites.</p>

<p>We were very few developers in a fresh new startup company. And as any typical Israeli startup company of these years our focus was to build and deliver our products as fast as possible.</p>

<p>There were about 5 developers all in all when each was responsible to cover products in multiple fields. As web developer I was responsible
to build and maintain company websites, Affiliates system and Billing front-end.</p>

<p>In the first year the development process was almost unmanaged. We got requirements and requests for development by email or during a short brainstorm meeting in our CEO (<a href="http://yoniassia.com">Yoni Assia</a>) office. We had no revision control system, neither bug tracking system. And it all worked fine, as soon as we were a small team.</p>

<p>About a year later, as our needs and requirements increased, we had to recruit more developers to the teams. R&amp;D teams started to grow. We got more and more emails with development requests which we passed from one to other. It was endless email threads which can be hardly tracked.</p>

<p>At this point we decided to install our first revision control system to make audit of changes - <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Visual_SourceSafe">Microsoft Source Safe</a>. It was a real pain in the a*s to use it. It was eventually replaced by SVN which is better, but in bigger teams we had a branch merge hell with it.</p>

<p>Later on we also installed simple and intuitive bug tracking system which we are still using - <a href="http://www.fogcreek.com/fogbugz/">FogBugz</a>. We have .NET stack here for 80% of our products, that was the main reason for using these tools.</p>

<p>We had dedicated QA team which did only &#8220;monkey testing&#8221;. We had no automation at all. No unit tests, integration test, test automation, performance test, load test. Nobody invested time in peer code reviews. Logs were a mess, same with monitoring. It was very hard to find and identify the source of the problem.</p>

<p>Our development was done on personal computers and we used them as our environments as well. Shared resources. Each team member could break others environment with his change.</p>

<p>No REST APIs at all, instead DLLs everywhere we need to communicate with other internal components.</p>

<p>Product lead R&amp;D but not the opposite. Developers has almost no power to decide.</p>

<p>We worked in waterfall software development methodology although it wasn&#8217;t formal. Our releases was very long and risky. It took months to release following by weeks to fix bugs of such big release.</p>

<p>And so on and on, you get the picture, right?</p>

<p>It was a nightmare&#8230;</p>

<p>In the next post I’m going to describe the current R&amp;D situation in <a href="http://www.etoro.com">eToro</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is DevOps and how does it help us?]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/04/14/what-is-devops-and-how-does-it-help-us/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-14T22:40:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/04/14/what-is-devops-and-how-does-it-help-us</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With this post I&#8217;m starting a series of DevOps related posts. What is it, the past, the present and the future of DevOps in <a href="http://etoro.com">eToro</a> R&amp;D.</p>

<p>Lets start with basics and then drill down and expand to more details.</p>

<h2>What is DevOps?</h2>

<p>A formal definition taken from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DevOps">Wikipedia</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>DevOps (a portmanteau of development and operations) is a software development method that stresses communication, collaboration and integration between software developers and information technology (IT) professionals. DevOps is a response to the interdependence of software development and IT operations. It aims to help an organization rapidly produce software products and services.</p></blockquote>

<p>Although it is a fine but &#8220;dry&#8221; definition, I like the more simple one found in <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/geekle/devops-5348895">this</a> presentation online:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>D</strong>ev<strong>O</strong>ps is an approach to bridge the gap between agile software <strong>D</strong>evelopment and <strong>O</strong>perations (IT).</p></blockquote>

<p>I&#8217;m not going to write here anymore about DevOps as you can just find below my short DevOps high-level presentation that I wrote and presented internally for <a href="http://etoro.com">eToro</a> R&amp;D employees last week:</p>

<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/18801475" width="597" height="486" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p>Hope you could understand from this presentation what is DevOps in general and what does it suppose to give us after implementation.</p>

<p>We have a very long way until it&#8217;s going to be implemented, but we are on the right path.</p>

<p>In the next post I&#8217;m going to describe in more details about <a href="http://etoro.com">eToro</a> past and how everything has started.</p>

<p>Keep on reading and as always, I will be glad to get your feedback. ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/04/05/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-05T14:13:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/04/05/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a very first post in my new minimalistic geek blog based on <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress">Octopress</a> framework for <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a> blogging.</p>

<p>It is supposed to be simple and easy to maintain. It supports <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown">markdown</a> writing only, has no Admin section and you have to commit changes to <a href="https://github.com/virtser/octopress">GitHub</a> in order to publish a new post. So if I make a spelling mistake or type, you can fork the repository, fix it and make a pull request. ;)</p>

<p>I used to have several blogs in the past. One was a photography blog based on Wordpress, another photo blog in <a href="http://www.tumblr.com">Tumblr</a> and the last one based on BlogEngine.Net with some own custom modifications was my personal blog.</p>

<p>All blogs I used to have, were in <em>Russian</em> only. It is my first attempt to write a blog in <em>English</em>. It supposed to serve all my <em>English</em>, <em>Russian</em> and <em>Hebrew</em> speaking friends.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m going to write here about the things that interest me and may be interesting to read for others as well. I&#8217;m going to share here stuff related to my workplace and hobbies. It is important for me to get feedback. So if you read a post and you care or have something to say about it, please comment or share with others. You can also subscribe to this blog <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/poisonsblog">RSS feed</a> to get updates.</p>

<p>I have to stop talking to myself as nobody read first blog posts&#8230;  :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
