<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[David Virtser]]></title>
  <link href="http://virtser.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://virtser.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-01T07:27:41+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://virtser.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Virtser]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[poison77@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is DevOps and how does it help us?]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/04/14/what-is-devops-and-how-does-it-help-us/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-14T22:40:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/04/14/what-is-devops-and-how-does-it-help-us</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With this post I&#8217;m starting a series of DevOps related posts. What is it, the past, the present and the future of DevOps in <a href="http://etoro.com">eToro</a> R&amp;D.</p>

<p>Lets start with basics and then drill down and expand to more details.</p>

<h2>What is DevOps?</h2>

<p>A formal definition taken from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DevOps">Wikipedia</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>DevOps (a portmanteau of development and operations) is a software development method that stresses communication, collaboration and integration between software developers and information technology (IT) professionals. DevOps is a response to the interdependence of software development and IT operations. It aims to help an organization rapidly produce software products and services.</p></blockquote>

<p>Although it is a fine but &#8220;dry&#8221; definition, I like the more simple one found in <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/geekle/devops-5348895">this</a> presentation online:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>D</strong>ev<strong>O</strong>ps is an approach to bridge the gap between agile software <strong>D</strong>evelopment and <strong>O</strong>perations (IT).</p></blockquote>

<p>I&#8217;m not going to write here anymore about DevOps as you can just find below my short DevOps high-level presentation that I wrote and presented internally for <a href="http://etoro.com">eToro</a> R&amp;D employees last week:</p>

<iframe src="http://www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/18801475" width="597" height="486" frameborder="0" marginwidth="0" marginheight="0" scrolling="no" style="border:1px solid #CCC;border-width:1px 1px 0;margin-bottom:5px" allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen> </iframe>


<p>Hope you could understand from this presentation what is DevOps in general and what does it suppose to give us after implementation.</p>

<p>We have a very long way until it&#8217;s going to be implemented, but we are on the right path.</p>

<p>In the next post I&#8217;m going to describe in more details about <a href="http://etoro.com">eToro</a> past and how everything has started.</p>

<p>Keep on reading and as always, I will be glad to get your feedback. ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2013/04/05/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-05T14:13:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2013/04/05/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a very first post in my new minimalistic geek blog based on <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress">Octopress</a> framework for <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a> blogging.</p>

<p>It is supposed to be simple and easy to maintain. It supports <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown">markdown</a> writing only, has no Admin section and you have to commit changes to <a href="https://github.com/virtser/octopress">GitHub</a> in order to publish a new post. So if I make a spelling mistake or type, you can fork the repository, fix it and make a pull request. ;)</p>

<p>I used to have several blogs in the past. One was a photography blog based on Wordpress, another photo blog in <a href="http://www.tumblr.com">Tumblr</a> and the last one based on BlogEngine.Net with some own custom modifications was my personal blog.</p>

<p>All blogs I used to have, were in <em>Russian</em> only. It is my first attempt to write a blog in <em>English</em>. It supposed to serve all my <em>English</em>, <em>Russian</em> and <em>Hebrew</em> speaking friends.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m going to write here about the things that interest me and may be interesting to read for others as well. I&#8217;m going to share here stuff related to my workplace and hobbies. It is important for me to get feedback. So if you read a post and you care or have something to say about it, please comment or share with others. You can also subscribe to this blog <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/poisonsblog">RSS feed</a> to get updates.</p>

<p>I have to stop talking to myself as nobody read first blog posts&#8230;  :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
