<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[David Virtser]]></title>
  <link href="http://virtser.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://virtser.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-08T22:38:34+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://virtser.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Virtser]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[poison77@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better dependencies management for a team]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2016/05/03/better-dependencies-management-for-a-team/"/>
    <updated>2016-05-03T20:07:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2016/05/03/better-dependencies-management-for-a-team</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*R9aL9QgxtcS_lXOcXODvSw.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p>When you are like me working in a team of web engineers, on a project which involves usage of external 3rd party libraries and you are using <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/"><em>npm</em></a> and/or <a href="http://bower.io/"><em>bower</em></a> to manage those dependencies, you probably will find it useful.</p>

<h2>The problem:</h2>

<p>When you are working in a team and you are not keeping the 3rd party dependencies as part of your repository. Someone decides to add/remove/upgrade some dependency, they modify <em>package.json</em> or <em>bower.json</em> files reflecting the change and submits the change into repository.</p>

<p>Now you pull those changes into your local copy of the project and unless you run manually <em>npm install</em> and <em>bower install</em> you won’t have those dependencies updated for you locally. Which in most cases result to build/run errors or inconsistency.</p>

<h2>The solution:</h2>

<p>As we are working with <a href="http://gruntjs.com/">grunt</a>, I wrote a small <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/grunt-local-deps-update">grunt task</a> which helps detect and update dependencies if <em>package.json</em> or <em>bower.json</em> files version was changed.</p>

<p>So from now on, when someone changes a dependency and bumps npm/bower version, grunt task will automatically update every team member local dependencies.</p>

<p>Which eliminates notifications, questions and increases productivity. :)</p>

<p>Feel free to use it: <br/>
<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/grunt-local-deps-update">https://www.npmjs.com/package/grunt-local-deps-update</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Grunt running from root directory]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2015/11/18/grunt-running-from-root-directory/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-18T21:46:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2015/11/18/grunt-running-from-root-directory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://gruntjs.com/img/grunt-logo.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>If you are a web developer and you are using <a href="http://gruntjs.com/">Grunt</a> as your default task runner, you probably in most of the cases use it from some inner folder of the project, something like &#8221;<em>client/app</em>&#8221;.</p>

<p>In this case, every time you want to work on your code using command like &#8221;<em>grunt serve</em>&#8221;, you need to change directory into <em>client/app</em> to run it all the time.</p>

<p>Below, I show you the way to make grunt commands work from root directory which makes your life more comfortable, eliminating the need switching to <em>client/app</em> directory all the time.</p>

<ol>
<li>Add in your original <em>client/app/Gruntfile.js</em> file the following code to let Grunt know the base directory location:</li>
</ol>


<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>module.exports = function(grunt) {
</span><span class='line'>  // Must have in order to work from root
</span><span class='line'>  grunt.file.setBase(__dirname);
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>  ...
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>}</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>2.. Add symbolic link in your root directory to original <em>client/app/Gruntfile.js</em> file:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>ln -s client/app/Gruntfile.js Gruntfile.js</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>3.. Create <em>package.json</em> in root directory with grunt as dependency and install Grunt:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>npm init
</span><span class='line'>npm install grunt --save-dev</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>4.. Run grunt from root to test it.</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>grunt serve</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>That&#8217;s it, pretty simple.
Hope you like it and use it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I recruited test automation engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2015/05/13/how-i-recruited-test-automation-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-13T11:20:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2015/05/13/how-i-recruited-test-automation-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/test_automation.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Before we begin, I just want to make sure that we are on the same page about what is  &#8220;Test Automation&#8221;. For me, it is a way to automatically validate that a real user experiencing the predicted application behaviour. For example: User click on a button which should open a new window. In this case we need to automatically validate that user is able to click a button and a window will show up with predefined text. <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test_automation">Wikipedia: Test automation</a></p>

<p>Ideally, I wouldn&#8217;t recruit a test automation engineer at all. I beleive that software engineers should be capable to test their own code (as part of &#8221;<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eating_your_own_dog_food">eat your own dog food</a>&#8221; concept) by writing unit, integration or end to end tests. It makes even a higher level of bond to the code that you are developing and need to maintain in the future.</p>

<p>But in reality, there are many reasons that might prevent you from living without QA position at all. It could be a culture of the organization that you are working in, legacy code that you need to deal with, could be the product nature that you are developing and etc&#8230; Moreover, you might need someone to own quality control in your organization.</p>

<p>My team was missing a QA person to take control of the product quality that we were  developing and take ownership of quality all in all. We wanted to do 80% of the testing automatically while covering the manual in the left 20%. I had a budget to recruit test automation engineer of junior to mid level.</p>

<p>How do you recruit a good junior engineer? You are looking for a potential which you need to find and validate by testing it. So I composed a simple exercise for test automation position interview. I gave it as homework after meeting a potential candidate which passed the initial screening.</p>

<p>I thought that it would be a nice exercise to use some SaaS tools to check our company website contact form. I choose to use <a href="https://saucelabs.com">Saucelabs</a> for test automation code execution in the cloud using Selenium web driver and <a href="https://loader.io">Loader</a> to do the load test.</p>

<p>I tried to make the test work myself, before I give this exercise for candidate, to make sure that it&#8217;s possible and to learn the field myself to feel more eligible. (I never did test automation before)</p>

<p>The main purpose of the exercise was to see how candidate can learn and deal with new tools, use them to write automation and summarize all his work in a document describing what and why it was done.</p>

<p>I sent the exercise as homework to few candidates asking them to send me results in 24 hours, including the test automation source code and document explaining the services and the work that was done.</p>

<p>Eventually I found this approach of testing candidates very effective. You could see weak candidates return partial test results or not returning results of tests at all. Strong candidates asked question and tried to accomplish the mission in the best way. Some even found bugs in our contact form by running their unique tests. :)</p>

<p>Hope you find it interesting. If you have any question, let me know.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[bash tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2015/05/12/bash-tips/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-12T11:14:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2015/05/12/bash-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/bash.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I wanted to share few Linux bash (terminal) tips I found to be useful for me over the last year.</p>

<h1>1. Commands</h1>

<p><strong>cd -</strong> goes back to previous directory you have been at. useful when you accidentally switch to root dir for example.<br/>
<strong>!!</strong> - repeats your last command. most useful if you forgot to add sudo to last command: sudo !!<br/>
<strong>fuser -k tcp/8080</strong> - to find and kill a process which is using port 8080.<br/>
<strong>history</strong>  - shows you the history of commands you executed)<br/>
<strong>history | grep &#8216;git&#8217;</strong>  - will show you all the history items with word &#8216;git&#8217; in it</p>

<p>And now try <strong>Ctrl-R</strong> in terminal to open history search and type the desired search pattern.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m sure you know that <strong>Ctrl-C</strong> cancels a process execution. Did you also know that <strong>Ctrl-Z</strong> pauses a process by putting it in background and releasing a prompt for you? To bring back the paused process type <strong>fg</strong> (ForeGround).</p>

<h1>2. Aliases</h1>

<p>You can also set some aliases for your most used commands in <strong>~/.bashrc</strong> file:</p>

<p>My aliases are:</p>

<p><strong>alias ll=&#8217;ls -alF&#8217;<br/>
alias la=&#8217;ls -A&#8217;<br/>
alias l=&#8217;ls -CF&#8217;<br/>
alias cd..=&#8221;cd ..&#8221;<br/>
alias node=&#8217;nodejs&#8217;<br/>
alias s=&#8217;http-server -o -cors&#8217;</strong></p>

<h1>3. Prompt</h1>

<p>As well as define custom prompt colors and git branch you are working on, like I have for example:</p>

<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/bash2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>More details on how to do it <a href="http://code-worrier.com/blog/git-branch-in-bash-prompt">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jasmine testing tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2015/04/19/jasmine-testing-tips/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-19T19:15:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2015/04/19/jasmine-testing-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are developing web application and you are working on client side, I hope you write unit tests or test automation or even both like we do. The following tips might be helpful if you write your tests using <a href="http://jasmine.github.io/">Jasmine</a> and execute it with <a href="http://karma-runner.github.io/">Karma</a> or <a href="http://angular.github.io/protractor/">Protractor</a>.</p>

<p>I guess you already know that if you want to disable a specific test you can add &#8220;x&#8221; before <em>describe</em> or <em>it</em> statements?</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>xdescribe('my beautiful function', function() {
</span><span class='line'> xit('having fun', function() {
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'> });
</span><span class='line'>});</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Did you also know that if you add &#8220;d&#8221; before <em>describe</em> or &#8220;i&#8221; before <em>it</em>, it will run only this specific test and skip the others?</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>ddescribe('my beautiful function', function() {
</span><span class='line'> iit('having fun', function() {
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'> });
</span><span class='line'>});</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This is especially helpful when you need to focus on debugging specific test.</p>

<p>Hope you liked it.
If you have more tips to share, please do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iVote]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2015/04/03/ivote/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-03T14:08:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2015/04/03/ivote</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/ivote.jpeg" alt="" /></p>

<p>A story about group of people who were passionate enough to try and make a change in Israeli elections process.</p>

<p><strong>TL;DR</strong> We successfully built a social voting application in few days of work in our spare time. Released it two weeks before recent elections in Israel and got 12,000 people registered and voted in that period. All by using viral Facebook marketing.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>It was a crazy idea of Tal Ben-Simon (VP Product of <a href="http://www.etoro.com/">eToro</a>), which he speeches me in the park. An idea to build a simple mobile application which is going to let people connect with their Facebook account, make their vote and see whom their friends has voted. All privately and anonymously of course.</p>

<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/ivote_screen1.png" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/ivote_screen2.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>In addition there is a campaigns section where you can write to your friends and try to influence them.</p>

<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/ivote_screen3.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>It doesn&#8217;t matter which political views you have. We built an application which is completely anonymous and it is not biased by any political movement. The goal of the application is to help you decide which party to give your vote for.</p>

<h4>The team</h4>

<p>We were few ex eTorians (Tal Ben-Simon, Orel Assia, Avner Sorek, Eyal Weiss, Lior Hakim and myself), who wanted to contribute, but not all of us had the time to do it. In addition Israel Roth (Co-Founder &amp; CTO at Labgoo) and Yosi Konigsberg joined this development effort. Guy Spigelman (CEO Israel at PresenTense) helped with marketing efforts.</p>

<p><strong>Tal </strong>was the product manager.<br/>
<strong>Orel</strong> was our UX/UI expert and designer.<br/>
<strong>Israel</strong> was responsible of native mobile integration and applications.<br/>
<strong>Yosi</strong>, <strong>Lior</strong> and <strong>Eyal</strong> covered the client side.<br/>
<strong>Avner</strong> helped developing sharing of results page using <a href="http://phantomjs.org/">PhantomJS</a>.<br/>
I was responsible of back-end, API, Database and Infrastructure.</p>

<p><strong>Guy</strong> who helped with marketing after release.</p>

<h4>The plan</h4>

<p>We started talking about this project three months before the elections, but couldn&#8217;t start building it as there was no clear development plan and the team wasn&#8217;t finalized yet. It was the same situation a month before the elections too, when Tal, Israel and myself just agreed and decided that if we don&#8217;t start now we won&#8217;t make it happen.</p>

<p>And that exactly what we did. Tal and Orel started to work on UI to make sure all materials are available upfront, before development start. I created technical design document, development plan and assigned tasks to team members by the level of their expertise.</p>

<p>We decided to build a hybrid web application and wrap it with mobile native wrapper. The app should work from modern desktop browsers (IE 9+), Android native and iPhone native apps.</p>

<h4>Tech stack &amp; Infrastructure</h4>

<p>As we were very short on time, the goal was to build application with minimum efforts, iteratively. Try to use SaaS as much as possible and base tech stack on our own skillset.</p>

<p>What was eventually chosen:</p>

<p><strong>Source control</strong> — <a href="https://bitbucket.org/">Bitbucket</a><br/>
<strong>Cloud hosting</strong> — <a href="https://dashboard.heroku.com/apps/ivoteorgil/resources">Heroku</a><br/>
<strong>Database</strong> — PostgreSQL<br/>
<strong>Back-end</strong> — <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</a><br/>
<strong>Front-end</strong> — <a href="https://angularjs.org/">AngularJS</a> + <a href="http://ionicframework.com/">ionic</a> framework.<br/>
<strong>Social feed</strong> — <a href="http://getstream.io/">Stream</a><br/>
<strong>Mobile wrapper</strong> — <a href="http://cordova.apache.org/">Cordova</a><br/>
<strong>Mobile Push</strong> <strong>notifications</strong> — <a href="https://www.pushwoosh.com/">Pushwoosh</a><br/>
<strong>Email notifications</strong> — <a href="https://mandrill.com/">Mandrill</a><br/>
<strong>Tracking</strong> — <a href="http://www.google.com/analytics/">Google Analytics</a>, <a href="https://mixpanel.com/">Mixpanel</a><br/>
<strong>Tasks management</strong> — <a href="https://trello.com/">Trello</a></p>

<h4>Architecture diagram</h4>

<p>The architecture was very simple:</p>

<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/ivote_screen4.png" alt="" /></p>

<h4>How we did it</h4>

<p>It is important to state, that all of us did this project as side, non profit project, while working full time in other jobs.</p>

<p>So we did few hackathons during weekends and few sleepless nights to make a progress. And two weeks before the elections, when we almost lost our hope to release something, we finally were ready to release our first desktop web application. Followed by Android mobile version few days later. We dropped iOS version as we had no more time to do it and considering the long approval process.</p>

<p>Then Tal <a href="https://www.facebook.com/tal.bensimon/posts/10152703546392011?pnref=story">wrote his first iVote post</a> in Facebook which got shared <strong>82 times</strong>! This is how it became viral. Most of our traffic came from Facebook without spending a dime. We saw and felt that people like it. We got a lot of traffic coming in our first days and got about 5,000 users registered a week after launch.</p>

<p>Now we started to monitor closely our traffic and performance. We had to do some refactoring to be more scalable.</p>

<h4>Statistics</h4>

<p>And after two weeks, just on elections day we had the following numbers:</p>

<p>-<strong> 30,000 </strong>unique users visited the website.<strong> - 12,000 </strong>registered users.<br/>
- <strong>11,500</strong> votes.<br/>
- <strong>200</strong> likes in our <a href="https://www.facebook.com/ivote2015">Facebook page</a>.<br/>
- <strong>5</strong> articles published in online media.</p>

<p>Google Analytics stats:</p>

<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/ivote_screen5.png" alt="" /></p>

<h4>Articles published in online media</h4>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.facebook.com/wallanews/photos/a.135402296495977.11530.135130956523111/845191165517083/?type=1&amp;fref=nf">Walla News</a> and <a href="http://tech.walla.co.il/item/2835923">Walla Tech</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.globes.co.il/news/article.aspx?did=1001016577#fromelement=hp_morearticles">Globes</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.haaretz.co.il/news/elections/ratz/.premium-1.2584949?&amp;ts=_1425986710325">Haaretz</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.mako.co.il/nexter-cellular/apps/Article-44c06fc793e0c41006.htm?sCh=3d385dd2dd5d4110&amp;pId=757332771">Mako</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/192422#.VRB785OUem1">Arutz Sheva</a></li>
</ol>


<h4>Wrapping up</h4>

<p>It was a crazy, both challenging and enjoyable journey. I had the opportunity to work again with people I love and meet new people I never had the chance to work with. Get more information and experience on mobile web and native development.</p>

<p>If you want to see the web app in action, the main website is located here:<a href="https://ivote.org.il/">https://ivote.org.il</a></p>

<p>And remember that “I have no time” is a lame excuse. If you really want it, you will make a time. Sleep less, do more. ☺</p>

<p>P.S.<br/>
<em>* The source code can be found </em><a href="https://github.com/virtser/ivote"><em>here</em></a><em>. If you want to make the same experiment in your country, please contact me. We will try to help.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WTFs/minute]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2015/01/26/wtfs-per-minute/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-26T09:16:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2015/01/26/wtfs-per-minute</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So true, about code quality.
The only valid measurement of code quality: WTFs/minute.</p>

<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/wtfm.jpg" alt="" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spotify engineering culture]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/12/15/spotify-engineering-culture/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-15T08:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/12/15/spotify-engineering-culture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m just going to put it here, as some great engineering culture references I beleve in:</p>

<iframe src="http://virtser.net//player.vimeo.com/video/85490944" width="600" height="412" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>




<iframe src="http://virtser.net//player.vimeo.com/video/94950270" width="600" height="412" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Google Culture]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/10/04/google-culture/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-04T13:03:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/10/04/google-culture</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/google.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Few weeks ago I joined <a href="http://www.spectory.com/en">Spectory</a>, a small projects outsourcing company with great culture and people.</p>

<p>My job is to form and lead a new team of software engineers. Our mission is to build a new strategic product for Google using modern client side technologies.</p>

<p>The challenge is huge - get to know new people (Spectory and Google), form a new team and build a new product.</p>

<p>As part of my job, I&#8217;m and my team deployed at Google and working closely with Google teams and other vendors. We need to integrate well to make a progress.</p>

<p>I wanted to share with you my observations of Google culture after few weeks of work. I share it because I think its interesting and some facts were surprisingly new for me:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Work with a smile. Engineers, security guys, cooks and cleaning stuff  are nice. Everybody are willing to help and actually suggesting their help. I still didn&#8217;t hear someone rising their voice.</p></li>
<li><p>Although we are sitting in an open space, it is pretty quiet here. This is leading to productive and focused work.</p></li>
<li><p>As a developer you get a very powerful machine. You can order any enhancement (keyboard, cables, headphones, etc..) that will make your work environment even more comfortable. Nobody will ask you to justify your order and you will receive it quickly.</p></li>
<li><p>On your first month you have to learn a lot to get introduced with Google unique tools and standards. Google have a lot of great documentation resources like code labs, wiki and internal user groups.</p></li>
<li><p>You have a lot of technologies and different tools you have to work with as engineer in Google. Engineers are free to choose which tools or technologies work best for them. Even every team can choose to develop their own work flow which suits best their culture and product they are working on. Still, standards you should apply to exists.</p></li>
<li><p>Requirements for new product development are usually not well defined and documented. It&#8217;s customer, product and engineering team responsibility to brainstorm and finalize it. Engineers have a lot of power to decide on product development paths and priorities.</p></li>
<li><p>Although it is an enterprise sometimes with its bureaucracy and politics, each team operates like a small start up. Trying to be as lean and iterative as possible delivering value fast to customers.</p></li>
<li><p>Last and most important aspect of this culture is the great professional  engineers working here. I think it wouldn&#8217;t be possible to build such culture without the people who get a lot of responsibility here.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>To be continued&#8230;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What have I learned from looking for a new job]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/09/15/what-have-i-learned-from-looking-for-a-new-job/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-15T01:23:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/09/15/what-have-i-learned-from-looking-for-a-new-job</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/linkedin.png" alt="LinkedIn views chart" /></p>

<p>I left eToro about 2 months ago and started to look for a new challenge. It was my first time actively looking for a job and trying to &#8220;sell&#8221; myself. :)</p>

<p>Below you will find a list of things I learned from the process of looking for a new job:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>If you can afford it, leave your current job before you found a new one. It gives you more time to look for a new job and you can do it transparently without hiding. That&#8217;s what I did.</p></li>
<li><p>At the beginning, you have to understand what kind of job and in which type of company you are looking for. This is good for training on your pitch and to make a focus. When you know what you are looking, you can decline job opportunities which looks less appealing for you.</p></li>
<li><p>Looking for a new job is fun. You have the opportunity to meet a lot of new interesting and sometimes inspiring people. Quit your job now! :)</p></li>
<li><p>Don&#8217;t trust recruitment agencies. Their recruitment procedures are outdated and not aligned with real market needs. Use social networks and your connections.</p></li>
<li><p>LinkedIn is working. Add a new company and call it &#8220;Looking for new challenges/opportunities&#8221; in your LinkedIn profile. You will receive 300% increase in profile views and at least one new job opportunity a day in your private inbox.</p></li>
<li><p>Look for people (team) and culture, but not for product, company or technology stack. You have to work with people at the end of the day.</p></li>
<li><p>It takes time to open your mind after a long period employed in one place. Meet old friends who were working with you and who you respect, see what they are doing. It will give you more ideas or maybe you can join forces.</p></li>
<li><p>Learn something new, you have plenty of free time now. Read books you always wanted to read, but couldn&#8217;t do it because you were busy at work. Learn that new technology and hack something. Spare more time with your family, kids, yourself. You won&#8217;t have this time for long.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Let me know what you think and if you have some other findings.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning client side development]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/09/11/learning-client-side-development/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-11T12:10:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/09/11/learning-client-side-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://bit.ly/1qIyl56" alt="" /></p>

<p>Writing this post of good learning resources as a reference for myself.</p>

<p>The purpose is to refresh a memory, skills and get updated with latest technologies like  HTML5, CSS3 and AngularJS.</p>

<h2>HTML, CSS and JavaScript</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.htmldog.com/guides/html/beginner/">HTML Dog&#8217;s HTML Beginner Tutorial</a></li>
<li><a href="http://diveintohtml5.info/">DIVE INTO HTML5</a></li>
<li><a href="http://learnlayout.com/">Learn CSS layout</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.bloc.io/build-your-first-website-with-html-and-css">Bloc&#8217;s Build Your First Website: A Crash Course in HTML and CSS</a></li>
<li><a href="http://learn.shayhowe.com/html-css/">Shay Howe&#8217;s Learn to Code HTML &amp; CSS</a></li>
<li><a href="https://dash.generalassemb.ly/">Dash by General Assembly</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.codecademy.com">Codecademy</a> - lots of great courses on HTML, CSS, Javascript, JQuery.</li>
</ul>


<h2>AngularJS</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://campus.codeschool.com/courses/shaping-up-with-angular-js/intro">Learn to build an application using Angular.js
</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.angularjs.org/tutorial">PhoneCat Tutorial App</a> official Google tutorial.</li>
<li><a href="https://thinkster.io/angulartutorial/a-better-way-to-learn-angularjs/">A Better Way to Learn AngularJS</a> by thinkster.</li>
<li><a href="https://egghead.io/articles/new-to-angularjs-start-learning-here">New to AngularJS? Start learning here
</a> by egghead.</li>
</ul>


<p>Feel free to suggest other resources.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Live page reload]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/09/08/live-page-reload/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-08T10:04:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/09/08/live-page-reload</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you are working with Sublime Text 2/3 and you want to be able to see live changes on your HTML/CSS layout, follow the steps below:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Find and install a new package from <a href="http://www.sublimetext.com/3">SublimeText</a> called &#8220;LiveReload&#8221;. Set <code>"save_on_focus_lost" :true</code> in user settings to enable auto save functionality.</p></li>
<li><p>Add <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/livereload/jnihajbhpnppcggbcgedagnkighmdlei">LiveReload Chrome extension</a> which you will have to enable in order to activate LiveRecord on page you are working at. Make sure to select in extensions management screen &#8221; Allow access to file URLs&#8221; to enable this functionality on local files as well.</p></li>
<li><p>Install and run free <a href="https://github.com/napcs/node-livereload">livereload node.js server</a> by running the following terminal commands:</p></li>
</ol>


<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ npm install -g livereload
</span><span class='line'>$ livereload [path]</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Deployment Pipeline with Jenkins]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/09/04/building-a-deployment-pipeline-with-jenkins/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-04T21:18:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/09/04/building-a-deployment-pipeline-with-jenkins</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Great presentation by <a href="https://twitter.com/noamshochat">Noam Shochat</a> about how we built our Continuous Delivery pipeline in eToro and which challenges we were facing:</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://virtser.net//www.youtube.com/embed/iBhpSyn7UmM?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Applenium]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/08/27/applenium/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-27T12:08:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/08/27/applenium</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just wanted to tell you about a very cool and groundbreaking test automation UI which was developed by <a href="https://twitter.com/maximguenis">Maxim Guienis</a>, my friend from eToro. It was designed for specific eToro needs to provide an easy &#8220;wizard like&#8221; tool for QA to write automatic UI tests.</p>

<p>It is called <strong>APPLENIUM</strong> (<a href="http://appium.io/">APPium</a> + <a href="http://www.seleniumhq.org/">seLENIUM</a>) and it uses Appium and Selenium frameworks as helpers to make mobile and web testing easy.</p>

<p>Find the <a href="https://github.com/bobmarthin/Applenium">source code</a> or get more information about it on his <a href="http://applenium.blogspot.com">blog</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Popular programming languages in Israel]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/07/31/popular-programming-languages-in-israel/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-31T17:30:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/07/31/popular-programming-languages-in-israel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some interesting numbers based on my LinkedIn research I did related to  choosing startup technology stack considering current situation on local market.</p>

<p><img src="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/Bt4SrvoIgAAlnQX.png:large" alt="" /></p>

<p>To get the data I just used Linked search and gave programming language name as keyword and filtered the results by location.</p>

<p>Hope you find it interesting and useful for you.</p>

<p>Do you think LinkedIn reflect the reality? Let me know what you think.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vagrant and Ansible]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/06/26/vagrant-and-ansible/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-26T16:08:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/06/26/vagrant-and-ansible</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I spend few hours recently to learn about <a href="http://vagrantup.com">Vagrant</a> and <a href="http://www.ansible.com/home">Ansible</a> to understand better how these tools work together. I&#8217;m really excited of potential hiding behind them. Unfortunately not many developers/companies know these tools and using them. So I wanted to share with you what I learned and hope it will help you to discover a concept called &#8220;Infrastrucutre as a code&#8221; if you didn&#8217;t know about it before.</p>

<h2>Vagrant</h2>

<p><img style="float: right" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/87/Vagrant.png" width="100px" hspace="5"/></p>

<p>Basically Vagrant provides you with functionality to create, provision and configure your own isolated development environment. It can be a single machine or number of machines connected in private network. Depends on your application infrastructure. All it does is creates on your laptop a defined set of virtual machines using (by default) VirtualBox. These machines actually defines your development environment.</p>

<p>Vagrant saves its configuration in <em>Vagrantfile</em> which is stored as part of your projects root. It should be also saved in source control as part of your project as it defines how your environment look like and how to create it from scratch if needed. Click <a href="https://github.com/virtser/vagrantansible/blob/master/Vagrantfile">here</a> to see how a typical Vagrant file looks like.</p>

<p><em>Vagrantfile</em> includes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Definition of your VMs (which boxes: Linux, Windows, etc&#8230;)</li>
<li>Network settings (port forwarding, private network, etc&#8230;)</li>
<li>Provisioning (how to setup a VM after creation from clean box)</li>
<li>and more other but less useful stuff&#8230;</li>
</ul>


<p>I won&#8217;t dive into more details. I hope you got the point and if you want to read more about why using Vagrant and what does it provide, you can go <a href="http://docs.vagrantup.com/v2/why-vagrant/index.html">here</a>.</p>

<h2>Ansible</h2>

<p><img style="float: right" src="http://bundles.kunstmaan.be/uploads/media/52f2178e8b342.png" width="100px" hspace="5"/> Ansible is a lightweight, simpler and easier to on board alternative for widely known Chef and Puppet configuration management tools. Like their big brothers its mission is to allow smart provisioning, deployment and configuration management of servers.</p>

<p>Ansible uses a <em>hosts</em> file to define how your environment look like. You can create groups of identical servers as well. Groups are good to define a set of similar machines for later mass provisioning. Example of such file can be found <a href="https://github.com/virtser/vagrantansible/blob/master/Ansible/hosts">here</a>.</p>

<p>Ansible saves its configuration in YAML files called &#8220;playbooks&#8221; which actually defines how to provision server or number of servers. Example of such file can be found <a href="https://github.com/virtser/vagrantansible/blob/master/Ansible/front.yml">here</a>.</p>

<p>Same as with Vagrant, you save these YAML files along side with your project, because they define how to build your environment.</p>

<p>You can read more about why using Ansible and what does it provide  <a href="http://www.ansible.com/how-ansible-works">here</a>.</p>

<h2>Vagrant and Ansible integration</h2>

<p>Vagrant as part of its configuration knows to call Ansible playbooks to provision the VMs that where created. It also automatically creates a hosts file to define the environment for Ansible and to make sure you will be able to provision the Vagrant machines from your laptop.</p>

<p>I don&#8217;t know if you heard the term &#8220;Infrastructure as a code&#8221;, but these tools actually does exactly that. Which means that you are writing code to define your infrastructure, saving it as part of source control and that you will be able to re-create it at any given time. Whenever it is in development, testing or production environments. That gives you great power to keep your environment infrastructure consistent, testable and repeatable!</p>

<p>Hope it was useful and made you think about how you should work. :)</p>

<p>I created the following example for you in GitHub if you want to play with it a little: <a href="https://github.com/virtser/vagrantansible">https://github.com/virtser/vagrantansible</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Measuring Business Values]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/02/11/measuring-business-values/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-11T21:51:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/02/11/measuring-business-values</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The following video is a little long, but its sooooo good! Please please please find time to see it.</p>

<p>It is talking about measuring business values through code and it&#8217;s  importance.</p>

<p>I think it&#8217;s a must see video for developers and product people, it can connect us better.</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://virtser.net//www.youtube.com/embed/czes-oa0yik?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why Graphite]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/02/04/why-graphite/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-04T20:58:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/02/04/why-graphite</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://graphite.wdfiles.com/local--files/screen-shots/graphite_fullscreen_800.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>There are many posts in the Internet about what is <a href="http://graphite.wikidot.com/">Graphite</a> and how to work with it. In this post I want to talk about why any professional engineer (developer) have to work with Graphite.</p>

<p>During my Graphite implementation sessions with engineers in <a href="http://www.etoro.com/">eToro</a> I felt difficulty to explain developers what is Graphite and why they want to use it instead (or in addition to) other monitoring tools.</p>

<p>We tried variety of different logging and monitoring tools in eToro in the last year. We are using log4net to save our logs in files. We used to work with <a href="https://logentries.com/">LogEntries</a> to store our logs in cloud, but we decided that it doesn&#8217;t precisely fit our needs and now we almost finished the migration to <a href="http://www.splunk.com/">Splunk</a>. Splunk knows to do logs analysis better in addition to aggregations, correlations and dashboards.</p>

<p>We are also using <a href="http://newrelic.com/">New Relic</a> which is a great SaaS tool. You just need to install an agent on your web server and you get a great visibility on your application performance including database and external dependencies. But we faced few problems with it. Most of our applications are written in .NET and some types of applications like WCF, Web API or <a href="https://servicestack.net/">ServiceStack</a> were not well supported by New Relic (could be that they added a better support by now) and returned wrong numbers if at all. In addition we found in some unknown cases that New Relic agent installed on IIS caused random application pool restarts.</p>

<p>And now before explaining why Graphite, I have to explain breifly about what is Graphite. Very rughly - Graphite is a metrics collector. You can report withing the code of your application counts, timers and gauges. You can count how many times some method in your application was called or the time it took to execute this method. You give your metric a name separated by dots and Graphite knows to break it and show it as a tree in its UI (see the screenshot above).</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>For example, you can count successful user sign ups by adding the following line in your code where you are sure that the sign up completed:</p>

<p><code>StatsdClient.Metrics.Counter("eToro.SignUp.Success");</code></p>

<p>or failed:</p>

<p><code>StatsdClient.Metrics.Counter("eToro.SignUp.Failure");</code></p>

<p>or measure the latency of sign up method:</p>

<p><code>StatsdClient.Metrics.Timer("eToro.SignUp", elapsedTime);</code></p>

<p>By the way, timers includes counters as well. You don&#8217;t have to count the call again if you time it.</p>

<ul>
<li>In this example I&#8217;m using <a href="https://github.com/goncalopereira/statsd-csharp-client">StatsD C# Client</a></li>
</ul>


<p>StatsD is a client which received the metrics by UDP, process it, applies some math function and stores it in Graphite. (this in not 100% correct, I wrote it as I wrote in favor of explanation  simplicity)</p>

<p>So now, when you have some high level clue about what you can do with Graphite, we will talk why we (as developers) have to use Graphite.</p>

<p><strong>Graphite advantages:</strong></p>

<ol>
<li><p>Once Graphite and StatsD servers are installed and all the required ports are open in firewall to accept UPD connections it requires absolutely no IT intervention, but only for regular daily monitoring and maintenance of up time. I mean that we, as developers, can independently add new metric to our code and it  will be immidiately created and shown in Graphite when you deploy the application to production.</p></li>
<li><p>Graphite gives power to developers. We control where to place our metrics, how do they behave and how we build our graphs based on these metrics. In case of New Relic, it is a black box, you never know when do they start to measure some metric and when do they stop. In case of Graphite you know exactly where to start measuring time and where to stop it, it gives you depth. We also have full control on the name of the metrics. You can include withing the code scope to metric name some dynamic parameters like &#8220;machine name&#8221; for example.</p></li>
<li><p>Graphite is non blocking. You report your metrics over UDP which is non blocking protocol. You can do it synchronously in your code and even if Graphite server is not responding, your application will work as usual.</p></li>
<li><p>Graphite knows to smartly aggregate your data and shrink it over time. You can define it for example to keep every second of data in the first week, then every minute in the first month, then every date in the first year. This way you don&#8217;t have to keep tons of metrics and you know exactly the file size of each metric.</p></li>
<li><p>Graphite is very easy to work with. After reporting a metric, it is a matter of one click on that metric and you can see your metric graph. You can easily drop one graph to another to merge them and see in one window. You can apply math functions on your graphs and save multiple graph windows as dashboards. And more&#8230;</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Ofcourse you can report counters and timers to your logs and then ask Splunk to collect the logs, process them and build some nice dashboards, but why? If you have like millions of lets say impressions or click you need to count? It make no sense to flood your logs with data which you want to see as graph. Logs are meant to keep your errors and debug info if required, keep them as clean as possible, otherwise it will be hard to analyse.</p>

<p>With Graphite you should measure every method in your application and all your external dependencies like database calls, cache hit/miss, messaging. Its up to you and your application business logic.</p>

<p>Another code example where we created a custom .NET [<em>GraphiteTiming</em>] attribute using  <a href="http://www.postsharp.net/">PostSharp</a> library in order to do quick metrics instumentation of each method in a class (if you set the attribute on class level) to measure time (and number of executions) in addition to counting the exceptions:</p>

<pre><code>[Serializable]
public sealed class GraphiteTimingAttribute : OnMethodBoundaryAspect
{
    [NonSerialized]
    private Stopwatch _stopwatch;

    public override void OnEntry(MethodExecutionArgs args)
    {
        _stopwatch = Stopwatch.StartNew();
        base.OnEntry(args);
    }

    public override void OnExit(MethodExecutionArgs args)
    {
            StatsdClient.Metrics.Timer(
                string.Format("{0}.{1}.{2}.{3}", 
                "ApplicationName", 
                System.Environment.MachineName, 
                args.Method.DeclaringType.Name, 
                args.Method.Name), 
                (int)_stopwatch.Elapsed.TotalMilliseconds
            );
        base.OnExit(args);
    }

    public override void OnException(MethodExecutionArgs args)
    {
        StatsdClient.Metrics.Counter(
            string.Format("{0}.{1}.error",
            args.Method.DeclaringType.Name,
            args.Method.Name),
            (int)_stopwatch.Elapsed.TotalMilliseconds);
        base.OnException(args);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>If you didn&#8217;t try Graphite yet, you should definitely do! It gives you &#8220;eyes&#8221; and power to see what is happening with your application in real time.</p>

<p>Like some wise man said, life of a good developer splits to two parts - before Graphite and after Graphite. ;)</p>

<p>Must read references to Graphite information:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://codeascraft.com/2011/02/15/measure-anything-measure-everything/">Measure Anything, Measure Everything</a></li>
<li><a href="http://matt.aimonetti.net/posts/2013/06/26/practical-guide-to-graphite-monitoring/">Practical Guide to StatsD/Graphite Monitoring</a></li>
<li><a href="http://blog.pkhamre.com/2012/07/24/understanding-statsd-and-graphite/">Understanding StatsD and Graphite</a></li>
<li><a href="http://steveakers.com/2013/08/01/span-vs-median-for-response-time-monitors/">Span vs Median for Response Time Monitors</a></li>
<li><a href="http://kevinmccarthy.org/blog/2013/07/18/10-things-i-learned-deploying-graphite/">10 Things I Learned Deploying Graphite</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[API Implementation]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/01/28/api-implementation/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-28T20:41:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/01/28/api-implementation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/api.gif" alt="" /></p>

<p>We are in the process of building of solid APIs for each of <a href="http://www.etoro.com/">eToro</a> main domains. It is not an easy task at all, as we didn&#8217;t invest too much in the past 7 years of eToro existence in all the architectural aspects of the system.</p>

<p>How services interact with each other? Who is responsible of doing what? What are the standards that we are working with? Which tools or technology do we choose for specific task? All these questions were not answered until now. Today we start to talk and think about it along with progressing with our first real API - <strong>User API</strong>. It is the place where it all begins - user created for the first time, user details updated, etc&#8230;</p>

<p>Today we still have one Users table in our big database which holds all our customer records in addition to their basic details and more irrelevant to user stuff. Each application can update (or read) this table from code without going through a dedicated API. The problem with this approach is that there is no <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Single_Source_of_Truth">single source of truth</a> - each and every service can apply its own business logic to change user related data, which leading to data inconsistency.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m taking active role of product/project manager for this API and leading the integration process with teams. Our main goals we want to achieve by User API implementation are:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Create the &#8220;Single Source of Truth&#8221;. All the requests to register user, update it&#8217;s details or get data of some user will pass through one API which hold the business logic of the user domain. We love <a href="https://servicestack.net/">ServiceStack</a> and we are using their framework for our REST APIs.</p></li>
<li><p>Provide notifications of user changes to different services via Pub/Sub instead of polling database for changes like we do today. We are using <a href="http://www.rabbitmq.com/">RabbitMQ</a> messaging here.</p></li>
<li><p>Separate User related data to it&#8217;s own dedicated database. This to isolate and encapsulate the user domain better. It will help in many aspects - automatic deployment of database changes with CD process, creation of environments with empty user database, other services won&#8217;t effect this database performance and vice versa. We are working with <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/data/tools.aspx">Microsoft SQL Server Data Tools</a> to accompish this</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Today the User API is almost ready, but can&#8217;t be completed because we need to migrate all the clients to use it instead of DB first. After all the clients which update customer records migrate, we will be able to enable caching, provide Pub/Sub functionality which can be trusted and eventually take out the user data our of the main DB to a dedicated one.</p>

<p>Lessons learned so far during the API building and integration process:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Don&#8217;t start it when it&#8217;s too late - invest in your architecture from the beginning or at least think about it. Now it takes so many time to make the integration and fix things which were done wrongly in the past.</p></li>
<li><p>Build a good plan - development plan (phases: establishment, optimization), integration plan (insert, update, select).</p></li>
<li><p>Don&#8217;t try to fix all evil at once, do it in small chunks, work iteratively. Otherwise it will hurt, it will bring more risk to migration.</p></li>
<li><p>Explain the importance of this move to the company - management and developers. It is required for engagement of people to give higher priority for integration than any other tasks.</p></li>
<li><p>Communication and follow up of progress are important to make the development and migration as fast as possible. You don&#8217;t want this project to take a lifetime.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Focus]]></title>
    <link href="http://virtser.net/2014/01/22/focus/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-22T16:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://virtser.net/2014/01/22/focus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://virtser.net/images/focus.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Lets talk about Focus and its importance in our life. Bear with me.</p>

<p>I recently spent few hour of my time explaining to my colleagues from <a href="http://www.etoro.com/">eToro</a> broad management about how important is to make a focus. Many times, as a startup, we tempted to join a new venture or not to loose another opportunity of business development.</p>

<p>Today, when we are not a startup company anymore, these temptations became a solid products which are not a core of our business and they defocus us from the real product. We have less time to invest to make our main product better because we have to support the other products which became not important anymore.</p>

<p>For example, historically we developed support for many types of payments and we keep on supporting all of them because some users want them. But instead, if we choose to support only Credit Card and PayPal, but do it good, even perfect, we could generate the same amount of volume if not even more!</p>

<p>If we build a good product, people will use it. Lets make such product, so even customers who have no Credit Card or PayPal account will want to create one just in order to try our product. Just like I did this week with <a href="netflix.com">Netflix</a>, which is available for U.S. customers only. I opened a US PayPal account and bought a US VPN to have US IP address and now I watch Netflix in my TV with <a href="http://www.google.com/intl/en/chrome/devices/chromecast/">Chromecast</a>. This is because they built amazing product!</p>

<p>So I spoke with about 10 people from company broad management about focus and how we can say NO to things which are not important. I hope that I could transfer the message.</p>

<p>Meanwhile I succeed myself to push and shut down few legacy products which were running for a long time on background and nobody thought to stop them. I also was involved in &#8220;not starting&#8221; a new products initiative which are not in our main business and I&#8217;m proud of it. Unfortunately some people take this initiative personally, but these are not my intentions.</p>

<p><strong>Say NO</strong>! It is more important to say what you are not doing than what you are doing, define non-goals. Make a focus on stuff that really matters, the deal breakers, the stuff that are core of your business. If you can use SaaS services, use them, don&#8217;t build it yourself. And of course you can apply this rule not just in your work, but in your real life.</p>

<blockquote><p>“People think focus means saying yes to the thing you&#8217;ve got to focus on. But that&#8217;s not what it means at all. It means saying no to the hundred other good ideas that there are. You have to pick carefully. I&#8217;m actually as proud of the things we haven&#8217;t done as the things I have done. Innovation is saying no to 1,000 things.” &#8211; Steve Jobs</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
